Start rolling.
Thank you very much.
I'm
gonna call to order the town of Andover Board of Selectmen regular meeting for Monday, December 12 at 7PM
with our first order of business, the Pledge of Allegiance.
I pledge allegiance to the flag of The United States Of America
and to the republic for which it is formed, one nation under God, indivisible,
with liberty and justice for all.
Okay.
We will get started with public speak. We'll start with Kimberly
Hawes.
>> Hi, I am here as a representative from the Rec Commission.
We're I'm just here to go over the cool memorandum of agreement when that comes up on the agenda.
>> Okay.
And Amy,
I'm assuming we'll wait for cool, or would you like to say something? Nope.
Nope. We can wait for cool. Thank you. And
Kerme?
Just here listening. Thank you. And
>> then we have CBC,
and we have Department of Public Works. So I think that's everybody. Is there anyone else that would like to sit there and participate in public speak if I'm missing?
Okay.
So we'll move on to item three, additions and deletions to the agenda.
I have one deletion to the agenda item
five, executive session, the union grievance.
Ask me the union is
the union and Eric have agreed to put that off.
Right.
And then
I would sit there and say, let's move
the truck
up so we can get
where was that item?
That was 11
AI.
>> 11 AI.
So let's move that up so Jay can go first.
Alright. Anybody else?
Paul, you good?
Good. Scott, you good? Good.
Good. Good. Somebody second that. Let's vote. Second. I second.
Alright. All those in favor.
Bye. Bye.
Good.
We're going to start with 11a
I,
discussion of the Freightliner of Hartford Nouplau.
Jay, you're up.
You're muted, Jay.
Sorry about that.
Yep.
>> So good evening.
I was able to get the quote updated
for the plow truck for this year.
I'm assuming you got everything in your packet
for the Freightliner.
>> And did you have a it's the same same truck that was quoted last year.
>> And
I don't know if you have any questions on that.
The, you know, basically
this, know, just
updated in pricing.
Everything remains the same.
The one thing that I didn't have at the time when I got this quotation
was the municipal
lease payments
options for a four year or five year.
And what were they Jay?
The lease payments?
>> For a four year
payment it's $71,772.46
five year
lease payments
$58.08
$8.09
$5
And
>> those prices are valid till
January
5 and then they would have to be updated,
you know, again, in case there's any adjustments to interest rates and whatnot.
>> Okay.
Eric, are are we
do we have this in our budget?
You're on mute.
On
mute, Eric.
>> Okay. I'll start again. So what we have in the budget is we have a public works equipment fund.
So
we don't have enough money and we won't in next year's budget
to outright purchase this.
And the reality is even if we agree to a contract now,
we're not going to have it until the next budget cycle.
The objective with
telling them we're going to buy it now
is that we stand a good chance of having it for next ball's plow season,
which is the objective.
Because we're not going to have enough money in the public works equipment fund to fund the outright purchase cause it's around $260,000
My
suggestion
is that we pursue
a,
you know, our lease options
for that piece of equipment.
K.
What's the payout at the end of it?
>> There should be no payout. It shouldn't there is it's not listed with any payout. It's just $5.05
well, depending on what you choose.
It's those payments
are equal payments.
>> Oh.
But basically, it's $30,000
of interest in the four year note and probably about
$40,000
of interest in the five year note.
>> Yeah. I didn't add them up.
Yeah.
What I do what they did tell
me that
if the contract
was agreeable
and all parties signed
the first pay excuse
me
the first payment
would be due
at the time of signing the contract
and held
in escrow
till delivery of the truck.
So
currently
there are build slots right now
available.
He said that he currently he's got 12 build slots
for next year,
which it's the fall, you know,
if we were able to act on this soon.
We could see a truck
before
winter.
>> Okay, and it's gonna be a silly question, Jay, but you're gonna tell me you need the truck, right?
>> Well, that's the plan.
Yeah,
I mean we have two trucks that we
fixed up this year
and you know, one of them will become the spare. The other truck,
you know, will send down the road.
>> Okay.
And when is the date that you need an answer by to get on this contract?
>> To get on this contract within the next There's couple a deadline on the quote.
Oh, this January,
for the
January 5 for this quote, which I
doubt will happen between now and you know the end of the month.
So, and typically between
now and
you know the next couple of months he's seen that prices doesn't you know as far as interest rates they don't really change that much, so it may not have
much effect on the bottom line
as far as the lease goes.
>> Well, we should put this on the top of our agenda for the next meeting. And so Eric and
Adrian and Jeff can all
weigh in on the financial ramifications of what we're doing. So what I would do is go back to the Freightliner gentleman and say, hey. Listen. The board of Selectman would like to go past their next meeting with this quote. Unless it goes down, of course, and then I wanna take advantage of it calmed down, which it won't go down. Yeah,
>> the only my
question for the board,
you know this is a state bid price
and we went through the
looking for trucks last year, do we have to go through
that process
all over again
seeing that this truck meets the qualifications
as far as purchasing, or is that for
finance,
CIP? Do we gotta
because I believe I got on their schedule as well.
Well,
>> let them tell you what they want done.
I mean, I'm assuming we have to follow
certain parameters within this new
purchasing
policy. And the question I would ask is just come prepared with the information from last year.
What were your numbers? Are they higher? Is it much higher this this quote from the state than what you were getting last year?
>> This one's
the new quote is just under the second bid for last year.
Although
It's
>> high it's higher than the bid we had last year for the one, you know, for the Freightliner.
It's about,
last year's price was $2.40,
for the truck and this year for Freightliner we're at,
maybe $2.59,
think we were at.
Many papers.
Yeah. $2.59.
Alright.
It's about $20,000
difference.
>> So unless the other members of the board want to sit there and
>> push this forward here, we can push this off to our next meeting? I think it would be wise to wait till next meeting. I think there's going to be maybe some questions or
just to give the other two members time to look everything over.
>> Okay.
Okay.
Alright, Jay. Do you have anything else you wanna share with us? Nope. That's it for tonight.
Jay, thank you very much. That's good. Thank you.
You, Jay. Thank you.
>> So we're gonna move to item four, the treasurer's report.
4A is the audit finding corrective action plan.
>> So
that wasn't meant to be in the packet. Sorry, that was my
bad proofing of the packet before it went out.
You've already seen that. So it's in there, but I don't think we really need to discuss
it.
And I don't have the sets of summaries
to provide you.
The only thing I would really like to talk about in that group is
item
B6,
which is the chart of account display options,
which I did put in the packet.
And so one of the things that had come out of the last
So we know we were going to QuickBooks and the question is what
is the data you're going to get every month look like?
And this is what the treasurer has
suggested
we provide, you know, just a profit and loss statement,
which shows the details,
you know, for both revenue and expense.
And there's not a lot of detail there.
There will be by the next time you see this.
And then the other question is how do we actually organize
the data to present it both to the board and to the public?
And this is my
best
guess or thoughts as to how it should be presented
overall.
So
I wanted to put it in the packet so you guys had
a chance to look at it. Reordered
some things. The actual numbering scheme comes from uniform chart of accounts. So, most of the numbering
isn't
going to change,
but how it looks
could change.
And so I've suggested this and we rearranged and grouped some things. So everything is there.
It just, it doesn't look like it did before. So I want to make sure you guys are all okay with it and the Board of Finance is okay with it before we lock that in as our final,
you know, how we're going to present it.
>> I have no problem with it, but you have to realize, Eric, that it's extremely easy to present the data in QuickBooks in multiple formats in any different way you want it. The
only thing that I would tell you that I would want on a monthly basis is a check register.
So I would like this information plus a check register provided to us so that we can sit there.
If we're not signing checks, we can actually see what disbursements the comm has made.
Sure.
Yeah.
Other
than that, Eric, it looks great.
>> Okay.
That's how it will be presented to you in the future. There's a lot of information
>> that's not
I mean, obviously it doesn't, you know, we haven't put deposits in. There's a lot of things that haven't been put in yet. So,
and I'm assuming what the treasurer has done has done journal entries to sit there and post all this?
>> That's
what she's in the process of doing right now. Okay.
>> Okay. And then
for next month, can you give us a report of what the status of the bank reconciliations
are?
Sure.
>> Mhmm.
That would be helpful. Hopefully, you got it all done. It's all up on QuickBooks and everything's right. So
We're getting there.
>> Looks good. Anybody got any questions?
Nope.
Okay.
Alright. So we're gonna move on to
well, we're skipping to item five because item five has been deleted.
So item six, board and commission presentations. Eric, do we have any?
We do not, as far as I know. Okay, excellent. Item seven, appointments. Do we have any?
We don't have any appointments.
Item eight, resignations.
No resignations.
Okay.
Item nine, town administrator.
>> So
I don't have a formal administrator's
report. What I wanted to spend my time going over is what I told you I would do at the last meeting,
which is present
a budget
overview
just of the things that are likely to have a significant impact on the budget coming up.
I don't want to do that right now. If you have any specific questions for me, I'd be happy to answer them, but I don't have a formal report for you.
>> K. Anybody got any specific questions they wanna ask Eric today?
Even though Eric hasn't been feeling well today and his stomach bothers me. So
anybody?
No? We're done.
Okay.
Item 10, old business.
Finance department employment,
status of the finance official.
Eric?
>> So we still don't I left that on there as a placeholder, but you as a board had asked me to hold off and advertise
basically
right after the holidays. So that's still my intention.
>> And, Eric, next month when we do this,
take the old business, right, and take the a away from discuss and act upon following.
Just do that for me, little side note. Alright. So we're about to see status of the community center RFP.
>> So
we're fairly far along.
We've
committee that you
we've committee that you appointed has sat down
and met and reviewed all of the
submissions that we had. We had five
total submissions.
And
we
have a meeting scheduled, I think on the nineteenth to bring the contractors back in,
at which point the goal would be to announce
who our preferred bidder
is,
and then
have a start contract negotiations
so that we come back to the Board of Selectmen
to approve a contract for it,
a design build contract,
potentially in January.
Adrian's
the committee chair, and that's what he was looking to do. All right. Can I ask one question?
>> For all the participants
on this call, can you mute yourselves,
everybody?
There's some feedback coming from
one computer or phone.
All right. So Brian,
if you are listening, can you mute yourself?
Thank you. I muted him for you. Now we oh, you got it? Okay. Yep.
So
do you need us to sit there and
make a motion at this meeting to give you permission to start contract negotiations?
I know we we have to get the contract back and approve it, but do you need anything from us?
>> Well, I I think if you're going to
empower the commission
to make that choice and bring you back a contract to sign,
then you'd have to make a motion allowing them to do that or allowing me to do that, for that matter. Well, I don't think
>> when you say a contract is signed, I mean, the Board of Selectmen has to approve one: whatever final contract is out there.
But I'm just asking you, in the interim state, do you need anything from us?
>> Well, think if you want to so
I was originally assuming that the Board of Selectmen themselves would want to take a recommendation
from the Commission and then formally
pick the bidder and then go into contract negotiations.
But that will take an extra month if we do it that way, as opposed to you authorizing the committee to make that decision
and then bring it back to the board at the approve a contract stage.
It kind of depends on what the board overall is comfortable with.
>> My
recommendation is we move this along quicker and we allow the
commission
pick somebody that they would like to sit there and start contract negotiations with, and
come back at the next meeting with a contract
that they want us to review and approve.
>> Aren't there
there's two of our board members on that committee already, I think. Correct?
Correct.
>> So
I I would feel comfortable with having the committee decide,
and like Jeff said,
come back and
give us an update.
>> Well, come back and give us a contract that they believe they've negotiated in an appropriate fashion.
Yeah. So, okay. So I make a motion that we allow the
Community
Center Commission to
go through the bid process, pick the
contractor that has the appropriate bid, and to start contract negotiations.
I'll second.
>> Any further discussion?
All those in favor, aye. Aye.
So
if it gets to the point, Eric, where you have
a low bidder or a bidder that you guys or a contract you believe is qualified, negotiate the contract and then bring it back to us, and we'll talk about it at our next meeting and approve it.
Okay.
10 d, the Hop River Homes update.
>> I don't have an update for you at this point. I know that's something we gotta get back on the burner.
>> Oh,
it's gonna be January.
October,
recognizing Andover residents.
Paula?
>> So maybe
I hate to push it off, but I wanted to get everybody's thoughts and
ideas on this program again. We were talking about,
the criteria,
how to how to have people nominate
other individuals and
and then how we were gonna decide. I I think we were all on the same page with how we were deciding we were gonna go into executive
session and vote about it. But
do we
do you feel comfortable talking about this and setting standards,
or do we wanna talk about this
next month again?
>> Let's
talk about it offline, and then we can all sit there.
Even though we're a public board, this is one of those things I don't think we we can do in public, so we have to figure it out. So maybe when the town attorney returns from Hawaii,
we can sit there and get some advice from him.
Good idea. Yep. Don't wanna drag it out. No. Let's just do it. Try to do something nice for the community, and
we'll
figure out how to do it correctly. Alright. So, 10 f, a cool program contract.
I know we all have the contract in our
packages.
So
I see that we have some cool members. So Jessica, how are you? Know that
Amy is here.
So
I think what we'll probably first do is,
Jessica, if you can, just
for the benefit of everybody, just walk us through the cool program
quickly and what you guys do, and then
we'll talk about your contract and what you can talk to us about what issues you might have with the contract.
>> Sure.
So
Amy and I feel that the COOL program before it's a before and after school program. It's separate from the summer camp,
so we run that. We have two classrooms in the school,
and we run that out of there.
And then the summer camp, we started a couple of years ago,
and we had partnered with the Parks and Rec Department
for the purpose of licensing
and insurance.
The first year that we ran the summer camp, we held our own insurance,
and then COVID happened.
And then
last year,
with the parks and rec department, they said that we didn't have to have insurance. That's why we didn't. However,
we have insurance policy now, which covers us twelve, months out of the year.
Our insurance policy was,
due December 1. That's why it took so long to get a policy
that covered the whole year.
I outsourced with another insurance agent, but they wouldn't look at our policy.
Our current policy,
agent
wouldn't
shop around until we were due. So initially, it was gonna go up $3,500
just to add the summer camp program.
However, we, were able to secure a policy that I emailed Eric Anderson on Friday,
and it has a coverage that you guys request.
Okay.
So our question is
why all of a sudden
do we need a contract with the town? We've gone to,
we've gone to the board of ed. We've gone to, town meetings when we were starting this program, and there was, not an interest from the Board of Selectmen initially.
So just wondering why all of a sudden there is a need for a contract.
>> Well, you have to sit there and and look at this board as a board that's trying to improve everything that's going on
Mhmm. In the past. And we
really do need that contract to sit there and tie up all the loose ends and all the things that haven't been done correctly in the past because school should
have had a contract for all of these years.
>> We
school is run out of the school,
and we we talk, and we have the support of Vowel, and we have the support of the board of education.
So the cool program, I don't understand it's run out of classrooms in the school. So what does the board of selectmen have to do with classrooms inside of the school?
>> Well, you're not wrong, but when you're utilizing
the
recognition
and some of the things that you're using,
>> we Not for cool. Not for cool. We don't use recognition at all for cool.
>> Okay.
So when we are sitting there looking at this and in the advice of the town attorney and what we're trying to do is just make sure that we're taking care of everything from a board of selectmen standpoint that we possibly can to protect the school, not the school, but the town and what we're dealing with.
So initially, our problem with the contract is
>> pool is mentioned several times in the contract. Well, who's who's the who's the entity? Who's the insurance in?
Our insurance is I gave Eric a copy. It's
Well, what's the entity name?
What do you mean?
Like, who is the policy carried under?
>> It's community organized and operated. Cool. That's why we would name cool.
Right. But I think what what Jess is saying is that we basically rent a space from the school.
So
if rent If this is space possible from from the the school
>> Ladies, if you would like the first section of the contract to be taken out,
we can talk to the town attorney on that. The second part of the contract, which is where all of the insurance is required,
is under the second part of this.
So
you tell us. If you would like that done, I'll sit there, I'll send it back to the town attorney.
>> Well, when you said
at a board of selectmen meeting back in the spring saying that you have talked to Eamon, you've talked to the board, and that basically you think that the town should run the program. And maybe you talked to us in 2017.
And then we have a contract in front of us that says basically that you guys
can if we do not if we do not fulfill its obligations under this agreement or the best interests of the town, you guys can stop our program within seven calendar days. I I This program is for
working parents as myself.
Yeah. This program is for working parents as myself.
Amy and I have took this program. We've created the summer camp,
and we've done very good things with it. As of right now, we do not need the parks and recs
help at all. We have secured our own insurance policy. We've been partnering with Val, our superintendent,
and getting summer grants for our summer camp program.
So at this point, we don't need any help from the parks and recs department. We
totally appreciate them helping us initially starting the summer camp program for the working families of Andover
so their kids have a fun and safe place to go to.
But moving forward, if you need us to sign a contract to rent the space
for the summer camp program, which would be the gym, which the board of selectmen or the town has ownership of,
we will be happy to do that. But as far as
signing a contract for cool, if there's any contract that should be signed, it should be with us and the board of ed, not with the town. Okay. So, Jessica, just so you understand,
>> my family took advantage of the COOL program before you guys were even there. So I totally respect what the COOL program is about and what it's doing.
If you understood when I talked to you about why I thought the town should have it, it's because the town could sit there and have an employee such as Amy, which I talked about,
involved in the rec commission and and doing other things for the community.
That is what I spoke to everybody about. That's what I still believe, but I understand
the problems of trying to run that within the town,
and that is why we're sitting there working with you guys in the way you're doing. You guys are doing a great job. Please do not take it the wrong way, and don't even think about it. I'm not sitting here
questioning what you guys are doing.
What I believe,
and I do believe this, is that if you look at most other communities around,
all their after school programs are run by the town or by the Board of Education,
and the individuals that are part of that are working with the town in other areas. So that's my that's my personal belief. I'm not here to sit there and say that that's happening.
We don't have the resources or the time to dedicate toward it. So what you guys are doing, what Amy and you are doing, greatly appreciate.
>> So don't take it the wrong way. Look at it from We a try to keep things minimal, and we try and keep it affordable for the parents of our town. You know, possibly, if you start having it run by the town, then the fees go up because now you're worrying about paying someone's insurance policy. You're worrying about paying salaries
where
we intentionally
work at bare minimum and keep it affordable for our families.
>> Isn't
so so I'm a I'm sorry. I'm a little confused.
So Jess
Jessica,
the the cool program is a nonprofit. Right? You have a board. Correct?
Yes. So I how
I don't and, Jeff, maybe this is a question that you can answer too. But
we we're not looking to take over the cool program. I don't even know how we could. Right? Because you guys have a board, and it's a nonprofit.
So it's not like we can go in and buy it out or anything like that. So
I don't I don't see where that could happen.
It would have to be, you know, conversations that would happen over time.
And in the contract
so did Dennis put in the contract?
And forgive me because I
this was updated on Friday, and I'm just looking at this now.
So
where it says if
it's if we're in failure if cool is in failure of you know this agreement the town can shut it down it's we're just talking that's just talking about the summer program
and then having cool be a part of
>> No. It's for both, Paula. It's for both. Yeah. Listen. It says it separately.
>> I'll sit there. I'll sit there and I'll tell you. I read this this afternoon.
Mhmm. I didn't like that. Yeah. Don't understand. So
>> I'm just here I wasn't going to approve this contract today at all.
I'm having a hard time It's time to understand what this board is saying.
That's a
those are certain things. That's why I asked you, what do you have problems with the contract? Okay.
>> So that's why I was confused.
Wasn't understanding how
we could say that we can have that language in there if
>> if Why would we ever why would we ever do that? The only the only time that anything would ever happen is if you had a catastrophe.
That would be the only time that anything like that would ever be executed, but it's still
something that you know? Anyway, just tell I'm gonna we we don't even have to have this in public. Please communicate with Eric.
Let's sit there and get changes made to this. And if the changes need to be made
and if you don't believe
it's a question for me, do we have any authority over the regular after school care program? Probably not, so it shouldn't even be in the contract anyway.
That's
fine. Listen,
this board is reasonable. We're not here to cause tremendous
problems.
I mean,
I'll still have the discussion with you, Jessica and Amy. I'll still have the discussion with you as to what
the after school program would be better served under
a community umbrella. There's no doubt about it. I mean,
Kuhl has been
active in some form
before my children, than my children were here,
in some form.
Is that the right way? That's questionable, but it's worked and it's done really good things for the town.
Making recommendations
on the contract, let's get them in place,
and let's move forward because, again, as I said, we do not have the resources to do it. It's not something that
I see happening in the near future, so we're gonna rely on your organization to sit there and continue to do it.
>> So
far moving forward, if we could have this conversation
about
the passenger van,
Do you, does the town of Andover still have the 16 passenger van?
Eric,
yes.
>> So Eric and your email to me, you had written
that,
if Amy got her CDL,
she could potentially drive the 20 passenger
van
because is there going to be a problem with in the past we've used a town driver,
but is there going to be a problem because they might not have a background check?
Driving the kids to and from the link lake?
So believe it's a 16 passenger van. You just need an endorsement. You don't need a CDL.
So if we could
use that,
that could solve
the problem of the,
town driver not having the background check.
>> I'm not trying to tell you what the legalities are
revolve
resolving with the cool program
driving.
I mean, if you want the 20 passenger van,
that definitely requires a CDL.
What the requirements are for the 16 for driving kids,
because it's not directly school related.
Honestly, I don't know.
It's just a public pastor endorsement.
>> I mean, you know, I keep,
I heard that,
you know, several people tell me that, and then for other things. And then when I actually re
looked into it, I realized we had been operating illegally for a long time.
What I'm saying is I don't want that liability.
I want to ensure that whoever's driving the kids, if it's a town vehicle,
you know, is legal to drive them in that situation.
And for me, the cleanest way to do it is to make sure if you have somebody with a CDL with their passenger endorsement,
you know you're covered.
So
that's my perspective. That's the cleanest way to do it. And I don't necessarily want to use town personnel to do it. And the reason is I flat out don't have enough drivers
to do that and meet the needs of senior transportation.
I mean, we still technically only have two drivers.
One of them is sick right now, so we're already scaling back for a couple of weeks
>> what we're doing internally. So so, Eric, that makes a lot of sense.
Jessica, let's find out about a 16 passenger van.
Okay. It's acceptable that Eric can we can all come back on a decision to make,
if it works, that he can drive a van.
Okay. We can sit there and not have an insurance issue
with our insurance coverage
our
insurer, then fine.
So let's find out the the rules and what's required, and let's try to see if we can do that. Alright. Our current policy,
>> covers the kids and
drive they they know that the kids are being driven places. So
I know so for our primary policy,
>> it will cover that. Correct. And your policy would cover it, and then our policy would end up covering it because it would be our vehicle. So let's make sure that we're legally driving the vehicles correctly. So if it's a certain type
of licensing,
then let's get the licensing done now. In the summer,
you guys can deal with that and reduce your costs even further and have an individual
take them back and forth. Okay.
Anything else related to the cool program that we need to talk about?
Scott,
Paula, anything?
Okay.
Alright. Thank you.
Welcome. Thank you, ladies.
>> All right. Eric, 10
gs, the zoning changes to the town property on School Road.
>> So I'm just giving you the heads up that we, the Board of Selectmen or the correction,
Planning and Zoning Commission does have a public hearing
coming up, which I believe is January
19,
and hopefully they will approve at that public hearing the
zone change
that will enable a community center to be built on the the town's property.
Okay. Just as a secondary thing,
the survey.
>> The survey, I have not checked in with them in the last couple of days.
At the beginning of last week, the surveyor was in doing the legal research in the town's records
and they had preliminarily
walked the property.
They had been planning on starting,
I think, last Friday.
So hopefully they're out there surveying
now.
>> Okay.
Anybody else have any questions related to that?
Nope.
Item
11, new business. Item I, the Freightliner of Hartford, the new plow. We have a discussion,
meeting schedule.
>> So you have
to select meeting dates for the upcoming year.
My suggestion is to go with the
essentially the same ones you've picked this year.
But now's the time when the board decides when it wants its schedule for next year's meetings.
>> The dates
in question are always the Mondays with holidays,
right?
>> So
July
is the second Monday, so that that should work.
And you get July August 14,
September 11.
I don't believe that's the holiday. So holiday is the third,
the fourth. The holiday is the fourth, so that's good.
The ninth,
the thirteenth, when is election day?
The seventh or the second Tuesday? When is election day, Eric?
2020? May.
>> Election you're talking about November
election day? Yeah.
It
is
is November 7.
2023.
So
that's a Tuesday.
Okay. So we can still do the thirteenth?
>> The
did you talk did you talk about October 9? Is you already talked about October 9? Is there a there a problem with October 9? That's,
Columbus Day.
>> Okay. So that's our one problem day. So when do you wanna do it on the tenth?
>> I think we usually I think for that month, we usually bump it to Tuesday,
or we could do the following Monday. I don't know if you wanna push it off a week or a day.
>> Just push it off a day.
So
that that appears to be the only problem month is October then.
Looks yep. That's the only one.
>> Okay.
So, Eric, if you can go with the second Monday in every month except October,
we'll have a meeting on 10/10/2023.
Okay.
Move on to
item 11,
triple I, opioid settlement allocation to towns,
the 820
some odd dollars. Eric, do we need to talk about it, or what do we have to sign to get our allocation?
>> So, we have our allocation.
We have the money. It's sitting in our bank account.
The problem is that
we have a hard time spending it
because it comes with a lot of strings attached.
So, I put in a memo.
We first asked,
you know, all the towns had asked the health board to come back to us with recommendations
of what the most logical and effective way
to spend that money.
You know, so that was that's
starting on page around 47
of your packet. That's the memo
from Rob Miller that talks about, you know, kind of what
the possibilities
are.
In our case, I think we're probably,
I mean, going to look at something like either just a straight donation to a treatment center, like community health resources
potentially,
or seeing whether
we could talk into running some kind of program and donating the money to them.
Frankly,
it's not a lot of money and it's too complicated to try to figure out how to spend the money ourselves on our own harm reduction program.
So the best thing we can
>> yep.
Find I mean, all I had in my head was does have
any program that could qualify?
And
donate the money to them. It's 855.
It was a huge, huge number. $8.56.
Let's round up, Scott.
So,
56.
Let's find somebody to donate it to. Is that times two, Eric?
No.
>> No.
I think we only have one
allocation
so far. We'll get basically one per year for like five years.
So, okay. So, you want me reach
out to and see whether they have a program that that would work for? Yes.
>> Okay.
Elevenfour
in the 824 referral to P and Z committee. So that's the meeting the public meeting this month?
Correct.
>> So I put a letter
in the packet, which is a memorandum I gave to the Planning and Zoning Commission
on behalf of the Board of Selectment.
Because
the Planning and Zoning Commission has to do what's called an eight-twenty
four statutory
referral
before
we put out a contract for the community center,
what has to happen
is
zoning
commission has to decide whether it's consistent with the plan of conservation and development or
not, and then report that back to the board of selectmen.
So I sent this to them on your behalf
since I know that you all want to
get a community center built.
So, they should be discussing
that at the December meeting.
My guess is they'll approve it right on the spot, but I'm not positive
their commission's,
you know, responsibility.
>> Okay.
Any questions on that?
Okay. So let's move to
eleven point five.
The twenty twenty three, twenty twenty four budget proposed time schedule, major factors affecting budget. So, Eric, you wanna put this off?
>> Yeah. So
I'm gonna share my screen here for a sec.
Okay, so I just wanted to go through before we get into the real nuts and bolts of budget season,
is just talk about kind of the big picture
and what things are likely to be driving the budget.
Obviously, this has been a tough year for a lot of people because of the inflation rate.
So, these are the things I want to talk about briefly.
One is personnel and administrative
costs.
Two is capital equipment,
building and maintenance, bridges and culverts, roadways,
energy costs. And then the last one is electrons.
So, under personnel and administrative costs,
we do have a reasonable contract in place with MEIU
and we are starting negotiations
with AFSCME on a retired contract
supposedly the first week in February.
Per the healthcare consortium,
the last number they gave us was to anticipate
an increase in the healthcare costs
of up to 8%.
You may have remembered,
last year our healthcare costs actually decreased
two to 3%.
But they're anticipating it will go up about 8% this year.
The other thing is that we don't have the state is
has not even talked about what number
the towns are going to have to come up with for MRF participation in the retirement program.
But given that the stock market is pretty well down,
I would anticipate we'll see an increase
in the town and individual contribution
to MRF.
But I really have no idea what that's likely to be.
And we're not going to get that from the state till like June
at the earliest.
The second thing is
changes in personnel.
There's really a couple of things we have to be aware of. The tax collector has formally
notified me that she will retire in the fall of twenty twenty three.
So,
as a group, we need to start talking about the possibilities
for replacement
and whether we try to hire somebody that's a tax collector
already, or do we hire somebody
with the intention of sending them through the training to become a tax collector
and how we want that transition
to look like? So, I think this spring we're going to have to tackle how we want to go about that.
The Chair of the Planning and Zoning Commission
indicated to me again that he's going to be advocating with the board
for a part time
town planner.
So, you're aware that you'll probably get that request.
And then the question is, what do we do in terms of staffing for the community center
once it's finished? That's something the board is going to have to consider
how you want to
address that.
Next item up is capital equipment.
So, if you look at the capital equipment plan for public works,
we've talked about purchasing a plow truck every five years.
So, we maintain three trucks
that are 15 years or older,
and with the reserve truck that's less than,
you know, 20 years old.
That's been our goal. We've been working towards that
over since around 2014.
So, bought one in 2014.
We bought one in
basically the winter of twenty
nineteen,
and then we'll have the next one,
the twenty three-twenty
four budget
cycle if we get on the bandwagon fairly quickly.
So,
would be the big ticket item that we would be looking at.
You know,
the fire department has indicated that
they're probably going to present the town with a proposal for purchase of a rescue engine
combo,
which would basically take two of the large public works or not public works, large fire department vehicles
out of service and replace it with a single combo unit.
But they're pretty expensive units.
You know, so I think the board has to anticipate that coming.
Whether the Board of Finance
and Board of Selectmen
agree with it or not, that's up to you. But I think you will kind of see that from the fire department.
I also think we should still consider
a Bolt EUV for senior transportation.
Just because I think this is,
you know, over the long term, it's a more economical way for us to be providing,
you know, medical transport,
which we do an awful lot of.
So, and this would be roughly
a $30,000
expenditure
if we considered it as a town.
So building maintenance,
you know, the community
center, we are proceeding with the RFP review at this time.
The assumption is that we have the funds currently
from the ARPA funds and potentially
some money from the Multi Use Building Fund.
The construction of the senior transportation garage at 15 Center Street,
that's largely grant funded.
However, it is anticipating
the use of about $75,000
from the multi use building fund
for the town's portion of that.
The renovation of the old town hall,
which will be done to satisfy the Connecticut,
the SHPO office,
So, we're able
to tear down the other building.
And then HVAC updates to the Andover Fire Department
and then also to the town hall.
The fire department would be paid for
out of the,
basically the fire department capital fund.
The HVAC updates to the town hall would be paid for with LOSIP funds.
You know, those are both would,
they would technically be in
probably
in this budget year,
but they're the next big, two big things coming up in terms of building maintenance.
Next item up is bridges and culverts.
So the replacement for Bunker Hill Bridge,
you know, we've been very fortunate to secure
complete funding for that.
We currently have around $450,000
in the bank
to help pay for that.
We're not going to be able to release that money because we'll have to pay that money to the contractor
initially,
but we will get fully reimbursed
for that bridge as well as the Long Hill Bridge.
The good news is we should have enough swing money in that fund right now that we don't need to add anything in future budget years.
And when both bridges are replaced, we should be able to roll that money back into the general fund,
which is good. So
we are proceeding with the design for the Hutchinson Road culvert replacement.
I'm hoping to meet with the engineer
next week
to start the ball rolling again on that.
At this point, I'm anticipating
we're going to use the state local bridge design program for that,
which provides 50%
funding.
However, I've been hearing some rumors that
I know some of the
COGs and also the Council of Small Towns
are pushing the state to use some of their federal,
you know, COVID relief and federal
IJA funds
to backfill
the culvert programs for the towns.
So, want to get to the point that we can set ourselves up to take advantage of that if they do increase
the percentage funding that the state will pay for those programs.
If I can get the state to pay for all of that, that would be even better.
But as it stands right now, we're looking at 50% funding for those.
We have enough money sitting in the bank to do the Hutchinson Road culvert replacement.
And then we kind of go from there and just keep
doing them as we can fund that project.
Roadways,
I think we're basically going to continue
with our existing program
of shimming and chip sealing roads.
We should again be working in the northern half of the town and fully complete shimming and chip sealing all the roads in the northern half of town. We're kind of working our way around the town counterclockwise.
And then we're also working on a trip grant
that will cover the cost of reclaiming and repaving
Skinner Hill Road
and Hendy Road.
So, you know, it's
a fairly long shot grant, but I'm sure there's going to be a lot of towns applying for it. But I think we can make a pretty good argument for why that should be funded.
Next up, energy costs.
Obviously,
and oil have been incredibly expensive
for a lot of people.
We've been very fortunate that we've been locked in
this year
at around,
I think $2.29
a gallon for both diesel and heating oil.
If we locked in today,
we would be locking in at around $3.8
a gallon for next year for heating oil as well as diesel.
The price has been coming down a lot this fall.
It seems like it's kind of bottomed out when it's going up a little bit down a little bit. If you look at it on a day to day basis. So my guess is it's about bottomed out.
But,
know, I don't know. Obviously, there's a lot of geopolitical factors that go into price of that too.
But if we locked in today,
we would still be looking at about a 40% increase
in costs for
both diesel and home heating oil
compared to what we're paying now.
Gasoline,
budgeted last year, we budgeted about $4 a gallon.
And when we started off in June, we were averaging about $4.30 a gallon, but obviously it's come under $4
and, you know, we're currently paying, you know, $3.50 $3.40 sitting on the same chair. And it still
seems to be coming down. So,
I would say next year, my guess would be we would budget about $3.50
a gallon.
So, we should actually be able to reduce our costs a little bit compared to currently.
Electricity,
you know, it's very hard to predict because
the
utility companies
basically,
you know, they bid out in six month
intervals
and
they haven't, there aren't any bids in for next year for electricity.
So it's pretty tough to tell what
our, you know, forecasts are electricity costs at this point.
So that covers utilities.
And the last thing that's kind of a big unknown
is
the state
adopted
a constitutional
ability
to hold early elections.
In other words, to keep the polls open
some length of time before the actual day of elections.
But there's nothing
right now
about how that's going to be done or how it can be done.
Where that comes where that's a concern to the town
is we have pretty old voting machines.
And if
we end up having to use the voting machines,
you know, and keep elections open for multiple days, you know, potentially even multiple weeks,
our voting machines aren't capable of doing running tallies.
So, we may actually be ending up looking at having to purchase new
election,
you know, counting machines
depending on what the state
decides.
And, you know, I have no idea whether that's realistic or not. Just, I don't know where the state's going with that. So,
in terms of the kind of overview,
that's what I have.
I'll send all this to you. I'll try to send this all to all the Board of Selected members tomorrow.
You know, that's just all food for thought as we're deciding
where we go with next year's budget.
The good news is it's not nearly as bad as,
you know, I thought it was going to be.
We're now starting to look at locking in potentially
heating oil
in the low $3 a gallon,
whereas a couple months ago we would have been locking in at
something in the fives.
So, we're definitely
better.
You know, that's all I got with that.
Unless you have any
questions or concerns about anything
there.
All right. Anybody have any questions, Paula,
Scott? No. No. Thank you, Eric.
>> Okay.
Okay. We'll move on to item 12, approval of immediate minutes for Monday, 11/14/2022.
Somebody make a motion.
>> I make a motion to approve the meeting minutes for Monday,
November 4 was it fourteenth?
>> Yes. Yep. 11/14/2022.
Second.
Alright.
All those in favor?
Aye. Aye. Item
13, the budget. Eric, do we have any appropriation transfers?
We do not.
Any
overexpenditure
requests, sign b?
Nope.
Not at this point.
>> Item 14, the tax collector's report.
It was in our package.
It was a heavy tax collection month
for
October,
so we don't have the November numbers ready.
That accurate, Eric?
As far as I know, that's accurate.
All
>> right.
There are
four refunds
to be processed,
all small dollars,
probably totaling under $400.
$332.51
total.
>> Yeah.
Looks about right.
Anybody want to make a motion on that one?
>> Scott, do you have it or you want me to do it? Go ahead.
Okay.
I'll make a motion to
set up tax refunds totaling
in $332.51.
Do I have to make do I have to say the names? No. You're fine.
>> Scott, you got a second then? I'll second that. Yeah. Alright. All those in favor?
Aye.
Okay. Item 15, department reports.
There were various departments that submitted their reports.
Do we have any questions related to any of them?
Eric, I have a question. How is the building department program going?
Do like the report that they're providing?
>> Think it's going very well.
You know, overall contractors
are all used to it. I mean, we do definitely,
not me personally,
but Lynn
does have to do a little handholding
with some applicants
that are putting in,
you know, building permit applications because as a lot of people know,
a lot of contractors get the homeowners to pull the permits
so they don't have to go through the hassle.
So, but overall, I think it's a huge improvement.
It makes it really easy to track what's happening, which is really nice.
And it makes it very easy to show,
you know, what we've pulled and in what category,
you know, and
to see both wetlands and zoning
and the building department all in one sheet.
So, overall, I think it's great.
The other thing is because the assessor's office has access to it,
it's very easy for the assessor to see what permits,
you know, are pulled so we can go out and do inspections.
You know, and we've actually found a fair bit of stuff lately
when we went out to inspect for one thing
and found a whole bunch of other things that either didn't get permitted
or
weren't inspected
when they were done. So, it's a good check. It provides a good check and balance that the assessor's office has that information directly.
>> Have you heard anything, Eric? Any complaints about
if somebody calls and it rolls over to Bolton that some of the permits that are in Andover are not showing up in Bolton?
>> So,
we had an issue.
So, sorry, I didn't mean to cut you off. So, we had an issue that I think we've gotten corrected
now.
We had updated our
phone tree,
but we
correctly
updated
the message.
So, if you were typing in the extension,
the extension went correctly.
But if you were just using the prompts, there was one prompt that was off. We had repeated one prompt twice.
So, there were things that were going to Randy Heckman's
cell phone, rolling to his cell phone,
that had been meant for
the zoning agent. And that was causing some issues.
I'm pretty sure we've gotten that straightened out now.
>> Okay. What about specifically
the permit,
looking up a permit? So I had a contractor that called
town hall.
It went to Bolton,
and they said
that they looked up
the permit for the Andover resident
and
they said in Bolton, it didn't exist.
But then Andover had it in our system.
Did you hear anything,
any other I don't know if it was just one situation,
but
did you hear anything like that?
>> That I haven't heard about. I mean,
if
the contractor wants to look up his permit,
he should go on Permit Link and look up his permit, and he'll see everything related to his permit. He shouldn't need to ask the building department to look up his permit.
He has access to all that information.
>> Yeah. So, guess the email never came through saying the permit was approved. So, but you're saying even before it's approved, they can look and see if it's in the system in Permit Link? Yeah, absolutely.
>> You know, once you put a permit in,
anybody can look on Permit Link and see that. But you as the individual
can log back into your account and you can read all the notes
in the exact status of that permit. That's kind of the beauty of the system is that,
you know, it enables
information to go directly to the customer,
you know, as long as you put in the correct email address and it's sending the stuff to the right spot. Okay.
Thank you.
>> Okay.
Any other questions related to any other reports that were in our packet?
Okay.
Item 16 correspondence.
Any correspondence
that we need to deal with?
Okay. Nope. Not that I know of. Alright. We're gonna go on to item 17, public speak.
Let's start with there's a phone number that's unmuted.
742-5475.
Okay. We'll move on. Joanne Ebert.
>> Hello,
I just have a quick comment that I
it's
unrelated to what's been said tonight. I think someone said it before, but I'm very happy that Dollar General
is in our town.
I think the whole building site it looks really nice
well kept
inside and outside it's the cleanest one I've ever seen.
I've heard a million
positive comments about it I know from looking on forums and different things people were really against it.
And I know the ins and outs but with going through the budget process tonight and everything and then hearing
you know already the increase that happened this particular year plus you know, going forward,
it's nice to have commercial tax bases in town and I think they for what it is, they did a really nice job. It looks good on that corner.
It looks a lot better than a lot of other places on Route 6. So I'm just pleased that we have something that came to town, you know, from start to finish listening to it, and it looks nice. So
>> that's all. Thank you. All right. Thank you very much.
Anne Kerme.
Okay
we'll move on Grace G.
>> Hi, I'm trying to turn on my camera here so you can see Dave and I. That's okay. I
guess it just won't work, sorry.
Hi, everybody.
Thank you so much for everything that you do for our town. And I know it's been a long evening, so Dave and I will keep this very, very short.
The reason we're here this evening is because we're asking for the board's support. We'd like to start an adult pickleball
game or night or however you wanna call it at Andover Elementary School.
And I understand there's
disc golf on Monday nights, there's volleyball on Friday nights, and
on Sunday night there's adult basketball.
However, I know that that leaves three nights and I understand that the kids do play basketball at this point in time. So we don't want to interfere with their time.
However, I think that once basketball season is done,
we'd like to see if there's something we can do to get that started. We currently play in Hebron two to three nights a week. I started playing in Marlborough.
So I know that in Columbia they have courts, in Colchester they do as well.
So
we're hoping that that's something that
the town of Andover can start as well.
And after talking with a few people at the town hall, I am going to be going to the Rec Commission meeting next month to discuss some specifics about that.
>> All right. Thank you very much. That sounds great.
Okay. Thank you. Good night. This is definitely the right place to be for that to get started.
I don't see anyone else on. Is there anyone else on that I'm missing? I don't think so. Nope.
Okay.
Item 18.
Motion to adjourn.
I'll second it, Scott, if you're not gonna.
Go ahead. I'll second it. All those in favor, aye.
All right, thank you very much, Eric. Thank you. I hope you're feeling better.
Have a good night.